If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we take a look at AMPK,
a fascinating enzyme
that acts as sort of
our body's fuel gauge.
In my book on everything
evidence-based in weight loss,
How Not to Diet, I had a section
entitled "Amping AMPK."
AMPK is an enzyme that acts
as a universal fuel gauge
for plants and animals,
revving up
when it detects a depletion
of the universal fuel.
The universal energy currency
in all of biology
is a molecule called
adenosine triphosphate,
commonly known as ATP.
The tri in triphosphate means
three, as in tricycle or,
in this case,
ATP's three phosphates
where energy is stored.
Plants make ATP
with energy from the sun,
and animals make it
by burning fat,
carbohydrates, and protein.
The energy is spent
by releasing the phosphates,
which transforms ATP to AMP,
adenosine monophosphate,
with mono meaning one,
which then can be juiced up
with two more phosphates
back to ATP,
and the cycle continues.
In this way,
every cell in our bodies
and in every living thing
is like a little
rechargeable battery.
AMP molecules are charged up
with phosphates to ATP
using sunlight or food
and then drained back down
to AMP
to do the cell's work.
This brings us to AMPK,
or AMP-activated protein kinase.
A kinase is a type of enzyme.
What might be the function
of an enzyme activated by AMP?
A buildup of AMP
means the rechargeable battery
is running low.
It's akin to the fuel gauge
in your car reading empty.
As the needle creeps toward
the E, what do you do?
Add more fuel.
But instead of having
an extra gas can in your trunk,
you may have junk
in the trunk,
fat stores on your body.
So that's what AMPK does:
It flips the switch
in your body
from storing fat
to burning fat.
That's why AMPK
is not only known
as the "master energy sensor"
in our body
but the "fat controller."
No wonder I featured it
in How Not to Diet.
But it can also control aging,
and so also plays
a starring role
in How Not to Age.
To sustain life,
each of our cell "batteries"
needs to stay fully charged.
This means maintaining a ratio
of about 100 ATP for every AMP.
So, our body needs
to perfectly balance
cellular activities
that consume energy
with cellular processes
that generate energy.
In times of plenty,
our cells can plow
full steam ahead.
However, in lean times,
which for animals
means not enough food,
and for plants
means not enough light
(darkness is like starvation
for plants),
AMPK kicks in
to reorient the cell
into conservation mode
and start tapping
into our energy stores,
like burning off body fat.
Our cells can also institute
a recycling program
called autophagy.
Autophagy comes from the Greek
words auto, meaning "self,"
and phagein meaning "to eat."
So, autophagy literally means
"self-eating."
It's a housekeeping process
by which defective
cellular components
like misfolded proteins
that had been allowed
to wastefully build up
in times of surplus
are broken down and scrapped
for spare parts.
This doubles as both salvage
operation and quality control,
scavenging raw materials
in scarce supply,
as well as clearing away
some of the buildup
of damaged debris
that is implicated
in the aging process.
As one review put it,
"The janitor
is the undercover boss."
This is one of the reasons
AMPK is increasingly recognized
as a pro-longevity factor.
AMPK induces autophagy,
which cleans house,
sweeps away accumulated waste,
and effectively institutes
a sort of cellular "reset."
There are three main ways
longevity researchers
establish an aging pathway:
Does the factor worsen with age?
If you amplify it,
does it accelerate aging?
And if you dampen it,
does it slow aging,
and thereby extend lifespan?
The loss of AMPK activity
as we age
fits all three criteria.
Our levels of AMPK drop
as we grow older,
and it gets harder to activate.
When this decline
is exacerbated,
aging is hastened (at least
in the hearts of mice).
And when this process
is reversed,
when AMPK activation
is boosted,
lifespan is extended
in model organisms,
as much as 38 percent
in a type
of microscopic roundworm
known as C. elegans.
Up and down
the evolutionary tree of life,
one of the most reliable ways
to extend lifespan
may be long-term
food restriction.
And AMPK activation is thought
to be one of the mechanisms
for this longevity boost.
What was remarkable about
the AMPK boosting experiments,
though, is that animal lives
can be extended
even though they were allowed
to eat as much as they want.
So, AMPK activators
can effectively fool the body
into thinking it is starving,
flipping it into
protective housecleaning mode
without having to suffer
the pangs of deprivation.
AMPK activators
can thereby be considered
calorie restriction mimetics,
or imitators.
No wonder AMPK is considered
a "druggable" target
for longevity.
But is there a way we can
naturally boost AMPK activation
to slow aging
without starving ourselves?
The answer is yes,
which we'll explore next.
How can we naturally boost
the enzyme AMPK
to slow aging
without starving ourselves?
AMPK is activated
by a fuel shortage.
If we don't want to limit
the amount of energy
going in through our mouths,
then we have to ramp up
the amount of energy
going out through our muscles.
Put people on a bike and start
taking muscle biopsies
while they cycle,
and you can detect a near
tripling of AMPK activation
within twenty minutes
in both diabetics
and nondiabetics.
That makes sense.
The muscles use up
the ATP to contract,
so AMP builds up
and AMPK is activated.
That may be one of the ways
exercise leads to weight loss.
AMPK activation also leads
to mitochondrial biogenesis,
meaning the formation
of extra mitochondria,
the power plants
within our cells
where fat is burned
and ATP is created.
So, AMPK doesn't
just cause more fat
to be shoveled
into the furnace,
it also causes more furnaces
to be built.
In this way, AMPK helps explain
why endurance training
eventually enables us
to run faster and farther.
So, might an AMPK activator
be like
the fabled exercise-in-a-pill?
Indeed, AMPK activation
can dramatically enhance
performance.
An AMPK-activator drug given
to sedentary mice for a month
boosted their running endurance
by 44 percent.
After one such drug
was discovered
at the famed Tour de France,
AMPK activators were banned
by the World Anti-Doping Agency.
So not just fasting in a pill,
but an exercise mimetic too?
People are often
"unwilling to perform
even a minimum
of physical activity..."
wrote a group
of pharmacologists,
"thus, indicating that drugs
mimicking endurance exercise
are highly desirable."
The "mass appeal" of such a drug
may tempt "big pharma"
to view physical inactivity
as a market to be medicalized
for profit."
But that vision
pales in comparison
to the universal market
for an anti-aging remedy.
In his essay
"On youth and old age,"
the Greek philosopher Aristotle
described death
as the loss of inner heat.
Indeed, the progressive loss
of function
of the estimated 10 million
billion mitochondria
spread throughout the body
is considered a core tenet
of the biology of aging,
but mitochondrial dysfunction
isn't just a consequence
of aging,
but one of its causes.
Dysfunctional mitochondria are
thought to actively contribute
to the aging process,
an insight illustrated
by a pioneering experiment
published over 30 years ago.
If you inject mitochondria
from a young animal
into a human cell,
nothing happens.
The cell doesn't appear
to notice.
Human skin cells average
about 300 mitochondria each,
and adding 10 to 15 extras
from a young rat
didn't appear
to have any effect.
But add the same number
of mitochondria from an old rat,
and the human cells start
showing signs of degeneration
within just a few days.
Even just having a few percent
of those old mitochondria
was enough to drive
the human cells
to an early grave.
So, age-impaired mitochondria
don't just become
less efficient,
but may become actively harmful.
So, if centenarian-equivalent
rat mitochondria are so toxic,
how do centenarian
human cells survive?
A group of Italian researchers
took some centenarian
skin biopsies to find out.
Skin samples
taken from the forearms
of young individuals
were compared to those
of elderly individuals.
As expected, each mitochondrial
mite from the older cells
was comparatively defective,
less efficient,
leaking free radicals.
But to the scientists' surprise,
the total amount of ATP
the centenarian cells
were pumping out
was even greater
than that of the younger cells.
How is that possible?
Because of a bulked up
mitochondrial mass.
It's like if an older Mike Tyson
took on a featherweight.
Even if pound-for-pound
the whipper-snapper's biceps
were more energy-generating,
Mike's sheer muscular mass
might prevail.
So how did the centenarian
mitochondria get swole?
AMPK.
Mitochondria can take up
anywhere between 2 percent
and 50 percent
of the volume of a cell
and are in constant motion,
merging together
and splitting apart
like the molten wax
of a lava lamp.
In times of starvation
or stress,
the fusing of individual
mitochondria together
into a large tubular network
can be advantageous,
in part by diluting
the effects
of damaged mitochondria
by mixing their contents
in with others.
AMPK appears to accomplish this
by tipping the lava lamp balance
from fission to fusion
by blocking
one of the proteins
necessary to break mitochondria
back apart.
This is thought
to be one of the routes
by which endurance exercise
can rejuvenate
mitochondrial function.
Thanks to AMPK,
working out may magnify
your mitochondria
as well as your muscles.
Our mitochondrial function
does decline with age,
in part through
the impaired ability of AMPK
to generate new mitochondria,
but AMPK can build
new cellular power plants,
expand existing ones,
and decommission old ones
(so-called mitophagy).
AMPK is said to serve
as a "mitochondrial guardian,"
and in that role
may help guard against
the ravages
of age-related disease.
If an AMPK activating drug
really could help us
reap the fat-burning
and health-promoting benefits
of fasting and exercise
without the hunger and sweat,
one could imagine
how it would become
one of the best-selling drugs
on the planet.
And it is.
It's called metformin,
prescribed more
than 90 million times a year
in the U.S. alone.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.